Finding aid to the Virginia Heim George papers SSC.MS.00221
Sophia Smith Collection
Virginia Heim George papers
1925-1981
Sophia Smith Collection
George, Virginia Heim, 1908-
SSC.MS.00221
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
Virginia Heim George was a YWCA executive, YWCA overseas secretary, and USO official. Most material in the George papers pertains to her foreign secretary work in South America and Czechoslovakia and her USO work in the Caribbean. Personal letters and travel diaries include descriptions of life in Brazil and the Caribbean and in post-war Czechoslovakia and West Germany. Material also includes speeches, clippings and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
1908 Born in St. Joseph, Missouri
1929 University of Wisconsin, major in economics
1929-40 Program Director, YWCA, working with industrial workers, Kansas City, Utica, Pittsburgh Camp Director, YWCA
1937 Carnegie Institute of Technology, graduate study in group work
1940-43 Executive Director, YWCA, Rio de Janiero, Brazil
1943-45 Regional Assistant Director of USO, Brazil, Caribbean Area
1946-48 Program Consultant, YWCA, Czechoslovakia, with two-week special
1948-51 National staff, YWCA, Community Division, working with business
1951-53 Group work and recreational director, YWCA, Oakland, California
1953-56 Executive Director, YWCA, Yakima, Washington
1956-66 Executive Director, YWCA, Utica, New York
1962-64 Advisor, YWCA, Taipei, Taiwan
1966-71 Advisor, YWCA, Colombia, with three short periods in Lima, Peru
1971 Executive Director, YWCA, Omaha, Nebraska
2003? Virginia Heim George died circa 2003
Scope and Contents
The Virginia Heim George papers consist of correspondence, diaries, clippings, and photographs. A major portion of the material dates from 1940 to 1948 and is related to her foreign secretary work for the YWCA in South America and Czechoslovakia and her USO work in the Caribbean.
The papers are divided into two series, PERSONAL and PROFESSIONAL. The PERSONAL material contains correspondence and diaries, both ranging from 1940 to 1981. The correspondence consists of letters to her family, mostly to her mother, with a small amount of incoming correspondence from family and friends, 1945-50. The nine diaries consist of six written between 1940 and 1948, plus three travel accounts from 1953, 1965, and 1981. Both the letters and diaries provide a detailed description of George's life while working for the YWCA and the USO. She was an eager and enthusiastic participant in her work and also took advantage of the opportunities it provided to travel extensively. She was a keen observer of the countries she visited and the people she met. Her wartime letters as well and those from postwar Czechoslovakia reflect the mail censorship of the times. As a result the diaries and the occasional letters that she was able to write freely are more candid. The diaries written from her two trips to Czechoslovakia in 1965 and 1981 contain particularly interesting accounts of life there, and the 1965 account reports earlier arrests and trials, particularly an incident involving the YWCA in 1948.
The PROFESSIONAL material consists of clippings and articles about George and her work, 1925-1975, three reports from her Czechoslovakia and Germany experiences, 1948, and a nine-page speech on the USO, ca. 1945. In this series are also fifteen photographs, five of the USO, six related to the YWCA, and four of women in Puerto Rico.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Personal
II. Professional
Additional Formats
Selections from the Virginia Heim George papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit "An Ever-Widening Circle of Friendship": YWCA Overseas Secretaries from China to Liberia.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Virginia Heim George Papers were a gift of Mrs. George in 1989.
Czechoslovakia--History--1945-1992--Sources; Brazil--History--20th century--Sources; Caribbean area--History--20th century--Sources; correspondence; diaries; clippings; photographs; George, Virginia Heim, 1908-; United Service Organizations (U.S.)--History--Sources; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--History--Sources; Young Women's Christian Association--South America--History--Sources; Young Women's Christian Association--World War, 1939-1945--War Work; George, Virginia Heim
- SERIES I. PERSONAL
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing to family
      - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 1944 Feb-Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 1944 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1945 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1945 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1946 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 1946 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1951-81 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Incoming
      - Mildred Heim Gumm (sister), 1945-50 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Friends, 1945-46; undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Diaries
    - Jul-Nov 1940 (Brazil) (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Jan-Feb 1941 (Brazil) (Box 2)
    - Jan-Feb 1943 (Brazil-San Francisco River trip) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1945-46 (Puerto Rico, Czechoslovakia) (Box 2)
    - 1946-47 (Czechoslovakia) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1947-48 (Scandinavia, Czechoslovakia; Switzerland) (Box 2)
    - 1959? (U.S. trip itinerary) (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1965 (Czechoslovakia) (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Czechoslovakia) (Box 2)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL
  - Clippings, articles, 1925-75 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Reports, speech, 1945; 1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photographs
    - YWCA, 1940-1943, 1960's (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - USO, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Brazil, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 24)